<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Here begynneth the lyfe of saynt Brandon</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1521</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16695</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3600</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108975</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844627</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844627</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9458</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16695)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9458)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 27:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Here begynneth the lyfe of saynt Brandon</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In the fletestrete at the synge [sic] of the sonne. By Wynkyn de Worde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Emprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1521?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Title page has woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B⁶ (signature collation from STC).</note>
                  <note>Cropped at foot, affecting signatures.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Brendan, --  Saint, the Voyager, ca. 483-577 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9458:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9458:1"/>
            <head>¶ Here begynneth the lyfe of ſaynt Brandon</head>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut representation of Saint Brendon, in monk's robes, with a book and crook or crosier, in a compartment with the device of William Caxton's mark and initials at the bottom</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="account_of_the_life_of_Saint_Brendon">
            <pb facs="tcp:9458:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aynt Brandon the holy man was a monke and borne in yrlonde / &amp; there he was abbot of an hous wherin were a thouſande mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes / &amp; there he had a full ſtrayte &amp; holy lyfe in great penaunce and abſtynence and he gouerned his mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes full vertuouſly / &amp; than within ſhorte tyme after there came vnto hym an holy abbot y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hyght Beryne to viſyte hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; eche was Ioyful of other &amp; than ſaynt bran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>don began to tell y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> abbot beryn of many wonders y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had ſeen in diuers lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des &amp; whan Beryn herd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of ſaynt Brandon he began to ſygh &amp; ſore wepte / &amp; ſaynt Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt wyſe he coude ſaynge / ye come hyther for to be Ioyfull with me / &amp; therfore for goddes loue leue your mournynge &amp; tel me what meruayles ye haue ſeen in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great ſee occean y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſeth al the worlde aboute / &amp; all other waters come out of him / whiche co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in all the partyes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erth / &amp; than Beryn began to tell ſaynt Bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don &amp; his monkes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meruayles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had ſeen full ſore wepynge / &amp; ſayd I haue a ſone his name is Meruoke / &amp; he was a monke of great fame / whiche had great deſyre to ſeke about by ſhyppe in dyuers cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trees to fynde a ſolytary place / wherin he myght dwell ſecretly out of the beſynes of this world for to ſerue god quyetly with more deuoco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n / &amp; I cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeyled hym to ſayle in to an ylonde ferre in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſee beſyde the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayne of ſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes whiche is ful well knowen. And than he made hym redy &amp; ſaylled thyder with his monkes / &amp; whan he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me thyder he lyked y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place ful wel where he &amp; his mon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes ſerued our lord full deuoutly. And tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Berynſawe in a vyſyon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this monke Meruoke was ſayled ryght ferre eeſtward in the ſee more than thre dayes ſaylynge &amp; ſodeynly to his ſemynge there came a derke cloude &amp; couered them that a great parte of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> daye they ſawe no
<pb facs="tcp:9458:2"/> light / &amp; as our lord wolde the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> away &amp; they ſawe a full fayre ylonde / &amp; thyder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they drewe / in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ylonde was Ioy &amp; myrth ynough &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ylonde ſhyned as bryght as the ſonne / &amp; there were the fayreſt trees &amp; herbes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer ony man ſawe / &amp; there were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny precyus ſtones ſhynyng bryght &amp; euery herbe there was full of fygures / &amp; euery tree full of fruyte ſo that it was a gloryous ſyght &amp; an heuenly Ioy tabyde there / &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there came to them a fayre yonge man &amp; full curteſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly he welcomed them al &amp; called euery monke by his na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me &amp; ſayd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were moche bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to prayſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of our lord Ihu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wolde of his grace ſhewe to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous place wher is euer day &amp; neuer night &amp; this place is called paradys terreſtre but by this ylond is an other ylond wherin no man may come / &amp; this yonge ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayd to them ye haue ben here halfe a yere w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out mete dry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke or ſlepe / &amp; they ſuppoſed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had not ben there y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of halfe an houre / ſo mery &amp; Ioyful they were there &amp; the yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge man tolde theym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place that Adam &amp; Eue dwelte in fyrſte / euer ſholde haue dwelled there yf y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had not broke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of god &amp; than the yonge man brought them to theyr ſhyppe agayne &amp; ſayd they myght no lenger abyde there / and whan they were all ſhypped ſodeynly this yonge man vanyſſhed awaye out of theyr ſyght / &amp; than within ſhorte tyme af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purueyau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of our lorde Iheſu they came to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> abbay where ſaynt Brandon dwelled / &amp; than he with his brethren recyeued them goodly &amp; demaunded them where they had be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo longe / &amp; they ſayd we haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> londe of by heeſt afore the gates of paradys where as is euer day &amp; neuer nyght &amp; they ſayd all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the place is full delectable / for yet all theyr clothes ſmelled of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwete &amp; Ioyfull place. And than ſaynt Brandon purpoſed ſone
<pb facs="tcp:9458:3"/> after for to ſeke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e by goddes helpe / &amp; anone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to puruey for a good ſhyppe &amp; a ſtronge &amp; vytayled it for ſeuen yere / and than he toke his leue of all his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne &amp; toke .xii. monkes with hym / but or they entred in to the ſhyppe they faſted forty dayes &amp; lyued deuoute<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly and eche of them receyued the ſacrament / and whan ſaynt Brandon with his .xii. monkes were entred in to the ſhyppe there came other two of his monkes and prayed hym that they myght ſayle with him. And than he ſayd ye may ſayle with me but one of you ſhall go to hell or ye come agayne / but not for that they wolde goo with hym. And than ſaynt Bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don bad the ſhypmen to wynde vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayle &amp; forth they ſayled in goddes name ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> on the morowe they were out of ſyght of ony londe and forty dayes &amp; forty nightes after they ſayled playne eeſt. And than they ſawe an ylonde ferre fro them. and they ſayled theyderwarde as faſt as they coude &amp; they ſawe a grete rocke of ſtone appere aboue all the water and thre dayes they ſayled aboute it or they coude gete in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place. But at the laſt by the purueeaunce of god they founde a lytell hauen &amp; there wente a londe euery thone and than ſodeynly there came a fayre hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; fell downe at the fete of ſaynt Brandon &amp; made hym good there in his maner / and than he badde his brethren be of good there / for our lorde hath ſente to vs his meſſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger to lede vs in ſome good place / &amp; the hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de brought them in to a fayre halle where they founde the tabbles ſpredde redy ſet ful of good mete and drynke. And than ſaynt Brandon ſayd graces / &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he and his brethren ſate downe and ete and dranke of ſuche as they founde And there were beddes redy for them wherin they to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke theyr reſt after theyr longe labour. And on the morne they retourned agayne to theyr ſhyppe &amp; ſayled a longe
<pb facs="tcp:9458:3"/> tyme in the ſee after or they coude fynde ony lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de tyl at the laſt by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> puruyau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god they ſawe ferre fro them a full fayre ylonde full of grene paſture wherin were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whyteſt &amp; greteſt ſhepe that euer they ſawe. For euery ſhepe was as great as an oxe &amp; ſoone after came to them a goodly olde man / whiche welcomed them &amp; made to them good chere / &amp; ſayd this is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ylonde of ſhepe &amp; here is neuer colde weder but euer ſomer &amp; that cauſeth the ſhepe to be ſo great &amp; whyte they ete of the beſt graſſe &amp; herbes that is ony where &amp; than this olde man toke his leue of them and badde them ſayle forth ryght eeſt and within ſhorte tyme by goddes grace that they ſhold co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me in to a place lyke paradys / wherin they ſholde kepe theyr eeſter tyde &amp; than they ſayled forth &amp; came ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter to that londe but bycauſe of lytell depth in ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce &amp; in ſome place were great rockes but at the laſt they wente vpon an ylonde wenynge to them they had ben ſaufte &amp; made theron a fyre for to dreſſe theyr dyner but ſaynt Brandon abode ſtyll in the ſhyppe &amp; whan y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fyre was ryght hote &amp; the mete nygh ſoden than this ylo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de began to moue / werof the monkes were aferde / &amp; fled anone to ſhyppe &amp; lefte the fyre &amp; mete behynde them &amp; meruayled ſore of the mouynge / &amp; ſaynt Brandon com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forted them and ſayd that it was a great fyſſhe named Iaſconie whiche laboured nyght &amp; day to put his tayle in his mouth but for gretenes he may not. And than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>none they ſayled weſt thre dayes &amp; thre nyghtes or they ſawe ony londe / wherfore they were ryghe heuy / but ſoone after as god wolde they ſawe a fayre ylonde full of floures herbes &amp; trees / werof they thanked god of his good grace / &amp; anone they wente on londe / &amp; whan they had gone longe in this they fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de a full fayre well and therby ſtode a fayre tree full of bowes / &amp; on euery
<pb facs="tcp:9458:4"/> bough ſate a fayre byrde / &amp; they ſate ſo thycke on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tree that vnneth ony lefe of the tree myght be ſeen the nom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre of them was ſo grete &amp; they ſange ſo meryly that it was an heuenly noyſe to here / wherfore ſaynt Bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don kneled downe on his knees &amp; wepte for Ioye / &amp; made his prayers deuoutly to our lorde god to knowe what theſe byrdes mente. And than anone one of the byrdes fledde fro the tree to ſaynt Brandon &amp; he with flekeryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of his wynges made a full mery noyſe lyke a fydle y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hym ſemed he herde neuer ſo Ioyfull a melody / &amp; than ſaynt Brandon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the byrde to tell hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe why they ſate ſo thycke on the tree &amp; ſange ſo merely / &amp; than the byrde ſayd. Somtyme we were aungelles in heuen / but whan our mayſter lucyfer fell downe in to hell for his hye pryde / &amp; we fell with hym for our offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces / ſome hyger / &amp; ſome lower after the qualyte of the treſpace &amp; bycauſe our treſpace is but lytell therfore our lorde hath ſet vs here out of all payne in full grete Ioye &amp; myrth after his pleaſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge here to ſarue hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on this tree in the beſt maner we can / the ſonday is a day of reſt fro all worldly occupacyon / &amp; therfore that daye all we be made as whyte as ony ſnowe for to prayſe our lorde in the beſt wyſe we may / &amp; than this byrde ſayd to ſaynt Brandon that it is .xii. monethes paſſed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye departed fro your abbey &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .vii. yere here after ye ſhal ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye deſyre to come to / &amp; all this .vii yere ye ſhall kepe your eſter here w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs euery yere / &amp; in the ende of the .vii. yere ye ſhal come in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> londe of byheſt / &amp; this was on eſter daye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the byrde ſayd theſe wordes to ſaynt Bran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>don / &amp; than this byrde flewe ayen to his felowes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſate on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tree / &amp; than all the byrdes began to ſynge eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſonge ſo meryly that it was an heuenly noyſe to here / &amp; after ſouper ſaynt Brandon &amp; his felowes wente to bedde &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:9458:4"/> ſlepte well / &amp; on the morne they aroſe by tymes / &amp; then<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e thoſe byrdes began matyns pryme &amp; houres &amp; all ſuche ſeruyce as cryſten men vſe to ſynge / and ſaynt Bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don with his felowes abode there .viii. wekes tyll trynyte ſondaye was paſt / &amp; they ſayled agayne to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ylonde of ſhepe / &amp; there they vytayled the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wel / &amp; ſyth toke theyr leue of that olde man &amp; retourned agayne to ſhyppe / &amp; than the byrde of the tree came agayne to ſaynt Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don / &amp; ſayd I am come to tell you that ye ſhall ſayle fro hens in to an ylonde wherin is an abbey of .xxiiii. mon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes which is fro this place many a myle / &amp; there ye ſhal holde your cryſtmas &amp; your eſter with vs lyke as I tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de you / &amp; than this byrde flewe to his felowes agayne. And than ſaynt Brandon &amp; his felowes ſayled forth in the occean / &amp; ſoone after fell a grete tempeſt on them / in whiche they were gretly troubled longe tyme &amp; ſore for laboured / &amp; after that they founde by the purueau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god an ylonde whiche was ferre fro theym / &amp; than full mekely prayed to our lorde to ſende the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thyder in ſaufte but it was .xl. dayes after or they came thyder / wherfor all the mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes were ſo wery of that trouble that they ſet lytel pryce by theyr lyues / &amp; cryed co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynually to our lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de to haue mercy on them &amp; brynge them to the londe in ſaufte / &amp; by purueaunce of god they came at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſte in to a lytell haue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / but it was ſo ſtrayte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnneth the ſhyppe myght come in / &amp; after they came to an ancre / &amp; anone y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> monkes wente to londe / &amp; whan they had longe wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked aboute at the laſt they fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de two fayre welles / that one was fayre clere water / &amp; that other was ſom what troubly &amp; thycke. And than they thanked our lorde full humbly that had brought them thyder in ſaufte &amp; they wolde fayne haue dronken of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water / but ſaynt Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don charged them they ſholde not take without lycence
<pb facs="tcp:9458:5"/> For yf we abſteyne vs a whyle our lorde wyll puruaye for vs in the beſt wyſe. And anone after came to them a fayre olde man with hore here &amp; welcomed them full mekely &amp; kyſſed ſaynt Brandon &amp; ledde them by many fayre welles tyl they came to a fayre abbey / where they were receyued with great honour &amp; ſolempne proceſſy on with .xxiiij. mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes all in ryall copes of cloth of golde and a ryall croſſe was before them. And than the abbot welcomed ſaynt Brandon &amp; his felawſhyp and kyſſed them full mekely / &amp; toke ſaynt Brandon by the honde &amp; ledde hym with his monkes in to a fayre hall / and ſette them downe a rowe vpon the benche / and the abbot of the place wyſſhe all theyr fete with fayre water of the well that they ſawe before / &amp; after ladde them in to the fratour and there ſette them amonge his couent &amp; ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne there came one by the purueyaunce of god / whiche ſerued them well of mete and drynke / for euery monke had ſet before hym a fayre whyte lofe and whyte rotes and herbes whiche were ryghte delycyous / but they wyſte not what rotes they were / &amp; they dranke of the water of the fayre clere well y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſawe before whan they came fyrſt to londe whiche ſaynt Brandon forbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de them. And the abbot came and chered ſaynt Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don &amp; his monkes and prayed them ete and drynke for charyte / for euery daye our lorde ſendeth a goodly olde man that couereth this table and ſetteth our mete and drynke tofore vs / but we knowe not how it cometh / ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we ordeyne neuer no mete ne dry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke for vs / and yet we haue ben .lxxx. yere here / &amp; euer our lorde worſhypped be he fedeth vs / we be .xxiiij. monkes in nombre &amp; eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry feryall daye of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weke he ſendeth to vs .xii. loues &amp; euery ſondaye &amp; feeſtfull daye .xxxiiii. loues / &amp; the brede that we leue at dyner we ete at ſouper / &amp; now at your
<pb facs="tcp:9458:5"/> comynge our lorde hathe ſente to vs .xlviij. loues for to make you &amp; vs mery togyder as brethren / &amp; al way .xij. of vs go to dyner whyles other .xii. kepe the quyer / and thus haue we done this .lxxx. yere / for ſo longe haue we dwelled here in this abbey And we came hyder out of thabbey of ſaynt Patrykes in yrlonde. And thus as ye ſe our lorde hath purueyed for vs / but none of vs kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth how it cometh but god alone to whome be gyuen honour &amp; laude world without ende. And here in this lond is euer fayre weder / and none of vs hath ben ſeke ſyth we came hyder / &amp; whan we goo to maſſe or to ony other ſeruyce of our lorde in the chyrche / anone ſeuenta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pers of waxe ben ſet in the quere &amp; ben lyght at euery ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me without mannes honde / &amp; ſoo brenne daye &amp; nyght at euery houre of ſeruyce and neuer waſte ne mynyſſhe as longe as we haue ben here whiche is .lxxx. yere. And than ſaynt Brandon wente to the chyrche with the ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bot of the place and there they ſayd euenſonge togyder full deuoutly. And than ſaynt Brandon loked vpwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de towarde the crucyfyxe / &amp; ſawe our lorde hangynge on the croſſe / whiche was made of fyne cryſtall &amp; cury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly wrought. And in the quere were .xxiiii. ſeetes for xxiiii. monkes &amp; the ſeuen tapers brennynge / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bottes ſeet was made in the myddes of the quere. And than ſaynt Brandon demaunded of the abbot how lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge they had kepte that ſcylence that none of them ſpake to other. And he ſayd this .xxiiii. yere we ſpake neuer one to another / &amp; than ſaynt Brandon wepte for Ioye of theyr holy conuerſacyon. And than ſaynt Brandon deſyred of the abbot that he &amp; his monkes myght dwel there ſtyll with him. To whome the abbot ſayd. Syr that may ye not do in noo wyſe for our lorde ſhewed to you in what maner that ye ſhall beguyded tyll the ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:9458:6"/> yere be fulfylled &amp; after that terme thou ſhalte with thy monkes retourne in to yrlonde in ſaufte / but one of the two monkes that came laſt ſhall dwell in the ylonde of ankers / &amp; that other ſhal go quyke to hell. And as ſaynt Brandon kneled in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyrche he ſawe a bryght ſhynyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gell / came in at the wyndowe and lyghted all the lyghtes in the chyrche. And than he flewe out agayne at the wyndowe to heuen / &amp; than ſaynt Brandon mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyled gretly how the lyght brenned ſo fayre &amp; waſted not. And than the abbot ſayd that it is wryten y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Moy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes ſawe abuſſhe all on fyre / &amp; yet it dyde not brenne / &amp; therfore meruayle not therof / for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> myght of oure lorde is now as great as euer it was. And whan ſaynt Bran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>don had dwelled there fro cryſtmaſſe eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tyll y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> twelfth daye was paſſed. Than he toke his leue of the abbot &amp; the couent &amp; retourned with his monkes to his ſhyppe and ſayled fro thens with his monkes towarde the ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bay of ſaynt Helarye. But they had great tempeſtes in the ſee fro that tyme tyll palme ſondaye. And than they came to the ylonde of ſhepe &amp; there were receyued of the olde man whiche brought them to a fayre hall &amp; ſerued them. And on ſhe erthurſdaye after ſouper he waſſhed theyr fete &amp; kyſſed them lyke as our lorde dyd to his dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyples. And there abode tyll ſaterdaye eeſter euen. And than they departed &amp; ſayled to the place where the gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te fyſſhe laye / and anone they ſawe theyr caudron vpon the fyſſhes backe / whiche they hadde lefte there twelue monethes tofore / and there they kepte the ſeruyce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſurreccyon on the fyſſhes backe and after they ſayled that ſame day by the mornynge to the ylonde where as the tree of byrdes was. And than the ſayde byrde wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comed ſaynt Brandon and all his felawſhyp / and wen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te agayne to the tree and ſange full meryly / &amp; there he
<pb facs="tcp:9458:6"/> and his monkes dwelled fro eeſter tyll trynyte ſondaye as they dyde the yere before / in full great Ioye &amp; myrth And dayly they herde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mery ſeruyce of the byrdes ſyt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynge on the tree. And than the byrde tolde vnto ſaynt Brandon that he ſholde retourne agayne at cryſtmaſſe to the abbey of monkes / &amp; at eſter thyder agayne / and the other dele of the yere labour in the occean in full gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te perylles / and fro yere to yere tyll the ſeuen yere be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complyſſhed. And than ſhall ye come vnto the Ioyfull place of paradys and dwell there .xl. dayes in full grete Ioye and myrth / and after ye ſhall retourne home in to your owne abbey in ſaufe and there ende your lyf and come to the blyſſe of heuen / to whiche our lorde bought you with his precyous blode. ¶ And than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aungel of our lord ordeyned all thynge that was nedefull to ſaynt Brandon and to his monkes in vytaylles and all other thynges neceſſarye to them. ¶ And than they thanked our lorde of his grete goodnes he had ſhewed to theym ofte in theyr grete nede and ſayled forth to the grete ſee occean abidynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mercy of our lorde in grete trouble and tempeſtes and ſone after came to them an horryble fyſſhe whiche folowed the ſhyppe longe tyme caſtinge ſo moche water out of his mouthe in to the ſhyppe that they ſuppoſed to haue be drowned / wherfore they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutely prayed god to delyuer them of that grete peryll And anone after came an other fyſſh gretre tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he out of the weſt ſee and faught with hym / &amp; at the laſt claue hym in thre pyeces &amp; than retourned agayne And than they thanked mekely oure lorde of theyr delyueraunce fro this grete peryl / but they were in grete heuynes by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe theyr vytales were nyghe ſpent / but by the ordy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunce of our lorde there came a byrde and brought to them a great braunche of a vyne full of rede grapes / by
<pb facs="tcp:9458:7"/> whiche they lyued .xiii. dayes / &amp; than they came too a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell ylonde / wherin were many vynes full of grapes / &amp; they there londed &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ked god / &amp; gadred as many gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes as they lyued by .xl. dayes after alwaye ſaylynge in the ſee in moche ſtorme &amp; tempeſt / &amp; as they thus ſayled ſodeynly came fleynge toward them a grete grype whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che aſſayled them &amp; was lyke to haue deſtroyed theym wherfore they deuoutely prayed for helpe &amp; ayde of our lorde Iheſu cryſte. And than the byrde of the tree of the ylonde where they had holden theyr Eeſter to fore. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grype &amp; ſmote out both his eyen / &amp; after ſlewe hym / wherfore they thanked our lorde. And than ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led forth contynually tyll ſaynt Peters daye. And than ſongen they ſolempnely theyr ſeruyce in the honour of the feeſt. And in that place the water was ſo clere that they myght ſe all the fyſſhes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were aboute them wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of they were full ſore agaſt / and the monkes counſeyled ſaynt Brandon to ſynge no more. For all the fyſſhes lay than as they had ſlebe. And than ſaynt Brandon ſayd drede ye not for ye haue kepte by two eeſters the feeſt of the reſurreccyon vpon the gretefyſſhes backe / and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore drede ye not of theſe lytell fyſſhes. And then<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e ſaynt Brandon made hym redy &amp; wente to maſſe &amp; badde his monkes to ſynge the beſt wyſe they coude / and than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>none al the fyſſhes a woke and came aboute the ſhyppe ſo thycke that vnneth they myght ſe the water for the fyſſhes / &amp; whan the maſſe was done all the fyſſhes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted ſoo as they were no more ſeen. And ſeuen dayes they ſayled al waye in that clere water. And than there came a ſouthe wynde &amp; droue the ſhyppe northwarde where as they ſawe an ylonde full derke and full of ſten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che &amp; ſmoke / &amp; there they herde grete blowynge and bla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtynge of belowes / but they myght ſe noo tynge but
<pb facs="tcp:9458:7"/> herde great thonderinge wherof they were ſore aferde and blyſſed them ofte / &amp; ſoone after there came one ſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge out all brenynge in fyre and ſtared full gaſtly on them with great ſtarynge eyen / of whome the monkes were agaſte / &amp; at his departynge fro them he made the horybleſt crye that myght be herde / &amp; ſoone there came a great nombre of fendes &amp; aſſayled them with hokes &amp; brennynge yron malles / whiche ranne on the water fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowynge theyr ſhyppe faſt in ſuche wyſe that it ſemed all the ſee to be on a fyre / but by the pleaſure of our lorde they hadde noo power to hurte ne greue them ne theyr ſhyppe wherfore the fendes began to rore and crye and threwe hokes and malles at them / and they than were fore aferde &amp; prayed to god for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte &amp; helpe for they ſawe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fendes al aboute the ſhyppe &amp; them ſemed than all the ylonde &amp; the ſee to be on a fyre / &amp; with a ſorowful crye all tho fendes departed fro them / &amp; retourned to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place that they came fro. And than ſaynt Brandon told to them that this was a parte of hell / &amp; therfore he char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them to be ſtedfaſte in the fayth For they ſholde yet ſe many a dredefull place or they came home agayne / &amp; than came the ſouth wynde &amp; droue theym ferther in to the north where they ſawe an hylle all of fyre / &amp; a foule ſmoke &amp; ſtenche comynge fro thens / &amp; the fyre ſtode on eche ſyde of the hyll lyke a wal all brennynge and than one of his monkes began to crye &amp; wepe full ſore &amp; ſayd that his ende was comen &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he myght abyde no len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in the ſhyppe / and anone he lepte out of the ſhyppe into the ſee &amp; than he cryed and rored full pyteouſly cur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſynge the tyme that he was borne &amp; alſo fader &amp; moder that begate hym bycauſe they ſawe no better to his cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reccyon in his yonge age. For now I muſt go to perpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuall payne. And than the ſayenge of ſaynt Brandon
<pb facs="tcp:9458:8"/> was verefyed that he ſayd to hym wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he entred / ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore it is good a man to do penaunce &amp; forſake ſynne for the hour of deth is incertayn And than anone the wyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de tourned in to the northe &amp; droue the ſhyppe in to the ſouth whiche ſayled ſeuen dayes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynually. And than they came to grete a rocke ſtondynge in the ſee / &amp; theron ſate a naked man in full great myſerye and payne. For the wawes of the ſee had ſo beten his body that all the fleſſhe was gone of / and no thynge lefte but ſynewes &amp; bare bones. And whan the wawes were gone / there was a canuas that hynge ouer his heed whiche bette his body full ſore with the blowynge of the wynde. And alſo there were two oxe tonges / and a great ſtone that he ſate vpon the whiche dyd to hym full great eaſe And than ſaynt Brandon charged hym for to tell hym what he was. And he ſayd my name is Iudas y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſoll<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de our lorde Iheſu cryſte for .xxx. pens whiche ſytteth here ſoo wretchedly / how be it I am worthy to be in the greteſt payne that is. But our lorde is ſo mercyful that he hath rewarded me better tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue deſerued For of ryght my place is in the brennynge fyre of helle. But I am here but certayne tymes of the yere that is fro cryſtmaſſe to twelfth daye and fro eeſter to wytſon tyde be paſte and euery feeſtfull daye of our lady &amp; eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſaterdaye at none tyll ſondaye that euenſonge be do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne but all other tymes I lye ſtyll in hell in full brennyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge fyre with Pilate / Herode &amp; Cayphas therfore accur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed be the tyme that euer I knewe them And than Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>das prayed ſaynt Brandon for to abyde ſtyll there all that nyghte / and that he wolde kepe hym ſtyll that the fendes ſholde not fetche hym to hell. And than he ſayd to hym with goddes grace / thou ſhalte abyde here all this nyght And than he aſked. Iudas what cloth that
<pb facs="tcp:9458:8"/> was that henge ouer his heed &amp; he ſayd it was a clothe that he gaue vnto a lepre / whiche was bought with the money that he ſtale fro our lorde whan I bare his purſe / wherfore it dooth to me full great payne now in betynge my face with the blowynge of the wynde. And theſe two oxe tonges that ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge here aboue me I gaue them ſomtyme to two preeſtes to praye for me / them I bought with myn owne money / &amp; therfore they eaſe me bycauſe the fyſſhes of the ſee gnawe on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſpare me And this ſtone that I ſyt on laye ſomtyme in a deſolate place / where it eaſed noo man / and I toke it thens and layde it in a foule waye where it dydde moche eaſe vnto them that wente by that waye. And therfore it eaſeth me now / for euery good dede ſhal be rewarded &amp; euery euyll dede ſhalbe punyſſhed. And on the ſonday ayenſt euen there came a great multytude of fendes blaſtynge and rorynge / &amp; they bad ſaynt Brandon goo thens that they myghte haue theyr ſeruaunte Iudas / for we dare not come in the preſence of our mayſter but yf we bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge hym to hell with vs. And than ſayd ſaynt Brandon I lette not you to do your mayſters commaundement but by the power of our lorde Iheſu I charge you to le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue hym this nyghte tyll to morowe. How dareſt thou helpe hym that ſolde his mayſter for .xxx. pens vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes / and cauſed hym alſo to dye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt ſhamefull deth vpon the croſſe. And than ſaynt Brandon char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the ſendes by his paſſyon that they ſholde not noye hym that nyght. And than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fendes wente theyr waye rorynge and cryenge towardee hell to theyr mayſter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great deuyll / &amp; than Iudas thanked ſaynt Bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don ſo ruefully that it was pyte to ſe and on the morne the fen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des came with an horryble noyſe ſayenge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had that nyghte ſuffred great payne by cauſe they broughte
<pb facs="tcp:9458:9"/> not Iudas and ſayd that he ſholde ſuffre double payne the .vi. daye folowynge &amp; they toke than Iudas trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blynge for fere w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them to payne. And after ſaynt Bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don ſayled ſouth warde thre dayes &amp; thre nyghtes &amp; on the fryday they ſawe an ylonde. And than ſaynt Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don began to ſynge &amp; ſayd I ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ylonde wherin ſaynt Poule the heremyte dwelleth &amp; hath dwelled there .xl. yere without mete &amp; drynke ordyned by mannes hon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / &amp; they came to the londe ſaynt Poule came &amp; welco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med them humbly he was olde &amp; forgrowen ſo that no man myght ſe his body Of whome ſaynt Bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don ſayd wenynge / now I ſe a man that lyueth more lyke an au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gell than a man / wherfore we wretches may be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that we lyue no better. Than ſaynt Poule ſayd to ſaynt Brandon / thou arte better than I for our lorde hath ſhewed to the moo preuitees than he hath done to me / wherfore thou oughteſt to be more prayſed than I To whom ſayd Brandon ſaynt / we be monkes &amp; muſt labour for our mete. But god hath prouyded for the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che mete as thou holdeſt the pleaſed / wherfore thou art moche better tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I. To whome ſaynt poule ſayd ſom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyme I was a monke of ſaynt Gatrikes abbey in yrlon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de &amp; was warden of the place where as men entre in to ſaynt Patrykes purgatorye. And on a daye there came one to me &amp; I aſked hym what he was. And he ſayd I am your abbot Patryke &amp; charge the that thou departe fro hens to morne erly to the ſee ſyde &amp; there thou ſhalte fynde a ſhyppe in to whiche thou muſte entre / whiche god hath ordeyned for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whoſe wyll thou muſt accom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plyſſhe / &amp; ſo the nexte day I aroſe &amp; wente forth &amp; ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the ſhyppe in whiche he entred / &amp; by the purueyu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god I was brought in to this ylonde the ſeuenth daye after. And than I left the ſhyppe &amp; wente to londe and
<pb facs="tcp:9458:9"/> there I walked vp &amp; downe a good whyle. And than by the purueyau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god there came an otter goynge on his hynder fete &amp; brought me a flynt ſtone &amp; an yron to ſmyte fyre within his two ſore clawes of his fete / &amp; alſo he had aboute his necke great plente of fyſſhes whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che he caſte downe before me &amp; wente his waye and I ſmote fyre &amp; made a fyre of ſtyckes &amp; dyde ſethe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyſſhe by whiche I lyued thre dayes. And tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the otter came agayne &amp; brought me fyſſhe for other thre dayes &amp; thus he hath done this .li. yere thorugh the grace of god / and there was a great ſtone out of the whiche our lorde ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de to ſprynge fayre water clere &amp; ſwete / wherof I dryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke dayly &amp; thus haue I lyued one &amp; fyfty yere &amp; I was forty yere olde whan I came hyder &amp; am now an hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and .xi. yere olde &amp; abyde tyll it pleaſe our lorde to ſende for me and yf it pleaſe hym I wolde fayne by dyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>charged of this wretched lyfe / and than he badde ſaynt Brandon to take of the water of the well &amp; to cary in to his ſhyppe / for it is tyme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou departe for thou haſt a great Iourney to do for thou ſhalte ſayle to an ylo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de whiche is forty dayes ſaylynge hens / where thou ſhalt holde thy ceſter lyke as thou haſt done tofore where as the tre of byrdes is &amp; fro thens thou ſhalte ſayle in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> londe of byheſt &amp; ſhalte abyde there forty dayes. And af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter retourne home in to thy countre in ſaufte. And than theſe holy men toke leue eche of other &amp; they wept both full ſore &amp; kyſſed eche other. And than ſaynt Brandon entred in to his ſhyppe &amp; ſayled eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xl. dayes ſouthe in full great tempeſt. And vpon eeſter euen came to theyr ꝓcuratour whiche made to them good chere as he had before tyme &amp; from thens they came to the great fyſſhe where they ſayd matyns &amp; maſſe on eſter daye / &amp; whan the maſſe was done the fyſſhe began to meue &amp; ſwa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me
<pb facs="tcp:9458:10"/> forth faſt in to ſee wherof the monkes were ſore agaſt whiche ſtode vpon hym / for it was a great meruayle to ſe ſuche a fyſſhe as great as al a countree for to ſwy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me ſoo faſte in the water / But by the wyll of our lorde this fyſſhe ſet all the monkes a londe in the paradyſe of byr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des all hole &amp; ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. And than retourned to the place he came fro. And than ſaynt Brandon &amp; his monkes than<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked our lorde of theyr delyueraunce of the great fyſſhe &amp; kepte theyr eeſtertyde tyll trynyte ſondaye lyke as they had done tofore tyme &amp; after this they toke their ſhyppe and ſayled eeſt .xl. dayes / &amp; at the forty dayes ende it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan for to hayle ryght faſt. And therwith came a derke myſte the whiche laſted longe after whiche fered ſaynt Brandon &amp; all his monkes &amp; prayed vnto our lorde for to helpe them. ¶ And than anone came theyr procura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour &amp; badde them to be of good chere for they were co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in to the londe of byheeſt. And ſone after that myſt paſſed awaye / and anone they ſawe the fayreſt countree weſtwarde that ony man myght ſe &amp; was ſoo cleere and bryght that it was an heuenly ſyght to beholde. And al the trees were charged with rype fruyte &amp; herbes full of floures. In whiche londe they walked forty dayes but they coude not ſe none ende of that londe and there was all way day &amp; neuer nyght / &amp; the londe was attem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perate / ne to hote ne to colde. And at the laſte they came to a fayre ryuer / but they durſt not goo ouer. And there came to them a fayre yonge man &amp; welcomed them cur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toyſly &amp; called eche of them by his name &amp; dyde great re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerence to ſaynt Brandon and ſayd to them be ye now Ioyfull / for this is the londe that ye haue ſought. But our lorde wyll that ye departe haſtely &amp; he wyll ſhewe to you more of his ſecretes whan ye come agayne in to the ſee / &amp; our lord wyll that ye lade your ſhyppe with
<pb facs="tcp:9458:10"/> the fruyte of this londe and hye you hens. For ye may no le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger abyde here / but thou ſhalte ſayle agayne in to thyn owne countre. And ſoone after that thou comeſt home thou ſhalte dye. And this water that thou ſeeſt here departeth the worlde a ſondre. For on that other ſyde of this water may no man come that is in this lyfe And the fruyte that ye ſe here is alwaye thus rype eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tyme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yere / &amp; alwaye it is here lyght as ye now ſe &amp; he that kepeth our lordes heſtes &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes at all tymes ſhall ſe this londe or he do paſſe out of this worlde. And than ſaynt Brandon and his monkes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of that fruyte as moche as they wolde and alſo they toke with theym great plente of precyous ſtones. And than they toke theyr leue &amp; wente to ſhyppe wepynge ſore bycauſe they myghte noo lenger abyde there. And than they toke theyr ſhyppe &amp; came home in to yrlonde in ſaufte / whome thyr bretherne receyued with ryght great Ioye gyuenge thankynges vnto our lorde, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che had kepte them all that ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yere fro many a peryll and brought theym home in ſaufte. To whome begy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen honour and glorye worlde without ende. Amen. ¶ And ſoo ſoone after this holy man ſaynt Brandon wexed feble &amp; ſeke / &amp; had but lytell Ioye of this worlde but euer after that his Ioye &amp; mynde was in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ioyes of heuen. And within ſhorte tyme after he beynge full of vertues departed oute of this worlde vnto euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge lyfe in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and was worſhypfully buryed in a fayre abbey / the whiche he hymſelfe fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded where our lorde ſheweth for this holy ſaynt many fayre myracles wherfore let vs deuoutly praye to this holy ſaynt that he praye for vs to our lorde that he haue mercy on vs to whome be gyuen lande honoure and empyre worlde, withouten ende. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:9458:11"/>
            <p>¶ Thus endeth the lyf of ſaynt Brandon. Emprynted at London in the Fleteſtrete at the ſynge of the ſonne. By wynkyn de worde.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>tripartite printer's device of Wynken de Worde, featuring William Caxton's mark and initials in central position; the sun, two blazing stars, and twenty small ones at top, the name Wynken de Worde a dog, a centaur and a centaur drawing a bow or Sagittarius at bottom(McKerrow 20)</figDesc>
                  <p>Wynken de Worde.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9458:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
